Chapter 123.
The musket.
During the most violent shocks of the typhoon, the man at the Peekquad's
jawbone tiller had several times been reelingly hurled to the deck by its
spasmodic motions, even though preventor tackles had been attached to it, for
they were slack, because some play to the tiller was indispensable.
In a severe gale like this, while the ship is but a tossed shuttlecock to the
blast, it is by no means uncommon to see the needles in the compasses at
intervals go round and round. It was thus with the Peekquads. At almost every
shock, the helmsmen had not failed to notice the whirling velocity with which
they revolved upon the cards. It is a sight that hardly anyone can behold
without some sort of unwanted emotion.
Some hours after midnight the typhoon abaded so much that through the
strenuous exertions of Starbucks and Stub, one engaged forward and the other
aft, the shivered remnants of the jib and for and main top sails were cut a
drift from the spars and when eddying away to lureed like the feathers of an
albatross, which sometimes are cast to the winds when that stormtossed bird is
on the wing. The three corresponding new sails were now bent and reefed, and a
storm tail was set further aft, so that the ship soon went through the water
with some precision again, and the course for the present eastsoutheast,
which he was to steer, if practicable, was once more given to the helmsman, for
during the violence of the gale he had only steered according to its
vicissitudes. But as he was now bringing the ship as near her course as possible,
watching the compass needle meanwhile, low, a good sign, the wind seemed coming
round a stern. I the foul breeze became fair.
Instantly the yards were squared to the lively song of ho the fair wind, oh ye
ho cheerily men, the crew singing for joy, that so promising an event should
so soon have falsified the evil portance preceding it. In compliance with the
standing order of his commander to report immediately, and at any one of
the 24 hours any decided change in the affairs of the deck, Starbucks had no
sooner trimmed the yards to the breeze, however reluctantly and gloomily, than
he mechanically went below to apprise Captain Ahab of the circumstance.
Air knocking at his stateateroom door, he involuntarily paused before it a
moment. The cabin lamp, taking long swings this way and that, was burning
fitfully, and casting fitful shadows upon the old man's bolted door, a thin
one, with fixed blinds inserted in place of upper panels. The isolated
subterraneousness of the cabin made a certain humming silence to rain there,
though it was hooped round by all the roar of the elements. The loaded
musketss in the rack were shiningly revealed as they stood upright against
the forward bulkhead. Starbucks was an honest, upright man, but out of
Starbucks heart at that instant when he saw the musketss, there strangely
evolved an evil thought, but so blunt with its neutral or good accompaniment
that for the instant he hardly knew it for itself.
He would have shot me once, he murmured.
Yes, there's the very musket that he pointed at me. That one with the studded
stock. Let me touch it. Lift it. Strange that I who have handled so many deadly
lances. Strange that I should shake so now. Loaded. I must see.
I I And powder in the pan. That's not good. Best spill it. Wait. I'll cure
myself of this. I'll hold the musket boldly while I think. I come to report a
fair wind to him. But how fair? Fair for death and doom. That's fair for Moby
Dick. It's a fair wind that's only fair for that oursed fish. The very tube he
pointed at me. The very one. This one I hold it here. He would have killed me
with the very thing I handle now. I and he would fain kill all his crew. Does he
not say that he will not strike his spars to any gale? Has he not dashed his
heavenly quadrant? And in these same perilous seas gropes he not his way by
mere dead reckoning of the error abounding log? And in this very typhoon
did he not swear that he would have no lightning rods? But shall this crazed
old man be tamely suffered to drag a whole ship's company down to doom with him?
Yes, it would make him the willful murderer of 30 men and more. If this
ship come to any deadly harm, and come to deadly harm, my soul swears this ship
will, if Ahab have his way.
If then he were this instant, put aside, that crime would not be his.
Is he muttering in his sleep? Yes, just there. In there, he's sleeping. Sleeping
I, but still alive, and soon awake again.
I can't withstand the old man. Not reasoning, not remmonstrance, not
intreaty wilt thou hearken to. All this thou scornest. Flat obedience to thy own
flat commands. This is all thou breathest. I and sayest the men have
vowed thy vow. Sayest all of us are Ahabs. Great God forbid. But is there no
other way? No lawful way. Make him a prisoner to be taken home. What? Hope to
rest this old man's living power from his own living hands. Only a fool would
try it. Say he were pinioned even knotted all over with ropes and hawers,
chained down to ringbolts on his cabin floor. He would be more hideous than a
caged tiger. Then I could not endure the sight, could not possibly fly his
howlings. All comfort, sleep itself, inestimable reason would leave me on the
long intolerable voyage.
What then remains?
The land is hundreds of leagues away and locked Japan the nearest. I stand alone
here upon an open sea with two oceans and a whole continent between me and
law. I I so is heaven a murderer when its lightning strikes a wouldbe murderer
in his bed tindering sheets and skin together? And would I be a murderer then
if and slowly, stealthily, and half sideways looking, he placed the loaded
musket's end against the door.
On this level, Ahab's hammock swings within, his head this way. A touch and
Starbucks may survive to hug his wife and child again. Oh, Mary, Mary, boy, boy, boy.
But if I wake thee not to death, old man, who can tell to what unsounded
deeps Starbucks body this day week may sink with all the crew?
Great God, where art thou?
Shall I? Shall I?
The wind has gone down and shifted, sir.
The four and main topills are reefed and set. She heads her course.
Stern all, oh Moby Dick, I clutch thy heart at last.
Such were the sounds that now came hurtling from out the old man's
tormented sleep, as if Starbucks voice had caused a long, dumb dream to speak.
The yetleled musket shook like a drunkard's arm against the panel.
Starbucks seemed wrestling with an angel, but turning from the door, he
placed the death tube in its rack and left the place.
He is too sound to sleep, Mr. Stub. Go thou down and wake him, and tell him, I
must see to the deck here. Thou knowest what to say.